A Guide to the James Burton Pond Collection 1838-1903
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
James Burton Pond Collection 1838-1903
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11130
This collection consists of ca. 210 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 210 items, 1899-1903, chiefly of holograph and typed drafts of biographical essays for the book, Eccentricities of Genius: Memories of Famous Men and Women of the Platform and Stage (New York: G. W. Dillingham, 1900) by James B. Pond (1838-1903), noted American lecture manager.
Contents List
- Manuscripts n.d. (Box 3)
  - "Brains," n.d., TMs (carbon), 80 p. (Box 1)
    an early unpublished draft of Eccentricities of Genius: Memories of Famous Men and Women of the Platform and Stage, by James B. Pond, with autograph revisions.
  - "Introduction" n.d., TMs, 22 p. (Box 1)
  - "Emma Abbott" n.d., TMs, 4 p. (Box 1)
  - "Lyman Abbott," with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 16 p. (Box 1)
  - "Felix Adler" n.d., AMs, TMs, 2 p. (Box 1)
  - "Susan B. Anthony" and "Elizabeth Cady Stanton" n.d., TMs, 3 p. (Box 1)
  - "Sir Edwin Arnold," with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 106 p (Box 1)
  - "Matthew Arnold" n.d., TMs, 5 p. (Box 1)
  - "P. T. Barnum" n.d., 2 TMs, 10 p. (Box 1)
  - "J. M. Barrie" n.d., TMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
  - "Henry Ward Beecher" n.d., TMs, 5 p. (Box 1)
  - ["James Berry"] n.d., TMs, 3 p. (Box 1)
  - "Josh Billings" n.d., 3 TMss, 20 p. (Box 1)
  - "Alexander Black" n.d., TMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
  - "Mrs. Maud Ballington Booth" n.d., TMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
  - "George W. Cable." First draft, with extensive autograph revisions and comments by George Washington Cable. n.d., TMs, 24 p. (Box 1)
  - "George W. Cable." Duplicate version not used n.d., TMs, 22 p. (Box 1)
  - "George W. Cable" n.d., AMs, TMs, 2 p (Box 1)
  - "Hall Caine" n.d., TMs, 17 p. (Box 1)
  - "Dr. Boyd Carpenter" n.d., TMs, 2 p. (Box 1)
  - ["Chickering Hall"] n.d., TMs, 6 p. (Box 1)
  - "Dr. Frederick A. Cook" n.d., TMs, 5 p. (Box 1)
  - "F. Marion Crawford" n.d., 2 TMss, 19 p. (Box 1)
  - "S. R. Crockett" n.d., TMs, 2 p. (Box 1)
  - "George William Curtis" n.d., 3 TMss, 6 p. (Box 1)
  - "Charlotte Cushman" n.d., TMs, 6 p. (Box 1)
  - "George H. Daniels," one with extensive autograph revisions n.d., 2 TMss, 10 p. (Box 1)
  - "Chauncey M. Depew" n.d., TMs, 10 p. (Box 1)
  - "Anna E. Dickinson" n.d., TMs, 2 p. (Box 1)
  - "Frederick Douglass," with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 3 p. (Box 1)
  - "William Henry Drummond" n.d., TMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
  - "Ralph Waldo Emerson" n.d., TMs, 5 p. (Box 1)
  - "John Fox, Jr." n.d., 5 TMss, 17 p. (Box 1)
  - "William Lloyd Garrison," with autograph addition by author n.d., TMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
  - "Patrick Sarsfield Gilmore" n.d., TMs, 17 p. (Box 1)
  - "William E. Gladstone" n.d., TMs, 2 p. (Box 1)
  - "Annie Grey" n.d., TMs, 15 p. (Box 1)
  - "E. Heron-Allen," with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 13 p. (Box 1)
  - "Rev. Newell Dwight Hillis," with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 7 p. (Box 1)
  - "Dean Hole" [Rev. S. Reynolds Hole], with autograph revisions n.d., 3 TMss, 27 p. (Box 1)
  - "Anthony Hope" n.d., 4 TMss, 35 p. (Box 1)
  - "Julia Ward Howe," with autograph revisions n.d., 2 TMss, 7 p. (Box 1)
  - "William Dean Howells," with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 11 p. (Box 1)
  - "Elbert Hubbard," with autograph revisions by Elbert Hubbard n.d., TMs, 12 p. (Box 1)
  - "Col. Robert G. Ingersoll," one with autograph revisions n.d., 2 TMss, 3 p. (Box 1)
  - "Sir Henry Irving" n.d., 2 TMss (Box 1)
  - "Joseph Jefferson" n.d., 2 TMss, 3 p. (Box 1)
  - "Clara Louise Kellogg," with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 3 p. (Box 1)
  - "George Kennan" n.d., TMs, 3 p. (Box 1)
  - "Rudyard Kipling" n.d., TMs, 5 p. (Box 1)
  - "Mary A. Livermore," with autograph revisions n.d., AMs, 2 TMss, 15 p. (Box 1)
  - "The Lyceum" n.d., TMs, 49 p. (Box 1)
  - "Hamilton W. Mabie" n.d., 2 TMss, 4 p. (Box 1)
  - "Joaquin Miller" n.d., TMs, 5 p. (Box 1)
  - "Nasby" n.d., 2 TMss, 4 p. (Box 1)
  - "Thomas Nast" n.d., AMs, 2 TMss, 9 p. (Box 1)
  - "Bill Nye" n.d., 2 TMss, 3 p. (Box 1)
  - "Nye and Riley" n.d., TMs, 5 p. (Box 1)
  - "John Boyle O'Reilly," one with autograph revisions n.d., 2 TMss, 5 p. (Box 1)
  - "Max O'Rell" n.d., TMs, 2 p. (Box 1)
  - ["Ozias"], with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 8 p. (Box 1)
  - "Thomas Nelson Page" n.d., TMs, 5 p. (Box 2)
  - "Dr. Joseph Parker" n.d., TMs, 7 p. (Box 2)
  - "William Parsons" n.d., 3 TMss, 4 p. (Box 2)
  - "Mrs. Parthington/Benjamin Penhallow Shillaber" n.d., TMs, 1 p. (Box 2)
  - "Lieut. Peary" [Robert Edwin Peary] n.d., 2 TMss, 7 p. (Box 2)
  - "Wendell Phillips," one with extensive autograph addition by author n.d., AMs, 4 TMss, 21 p. (Box 2)
  - "Gen. Horace Porter" n.d., TMs, 9 p. (Box 2)
  - "Bishop Potter" n.d., TMs, 2 p. (Box 2)
  - "Helen Potter" n.d., TMs, 1 p. (Box 2)
  - ["Richard A. and Mary Proctor"], with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 16 p. (Box 2)
  - "James Redpath," with autograph revisions n.d., TMsS, 19 p. (Box 2)
  - "James Redpath" n.d., 2 TMss, 28 p. (Box 2)
  - "James Whitcomb Riley" n.d., AMs, 2 TMss, 3 p. (Box 2)
  - "Charles H. Spurgeon" n.d., TMs, 18 p. (Box 2)
  - "Henry M. Stanley n.d., AMs, 4 p. (Box 2)
  - "John L. Stoddard" n.d., TMs, 2 p. (Box 2)
  - ["Harriet Beecher Stowe"], with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 12 p. (Box 2)
  - "Charles William Stubbs," with autograph revisions n.d., TMs, 29 p. (Box 2)
  - ["Rev. T. DeWitt Talmage"], with extensive autograph revisions and additions n.d., TMs, 35 p. (Box 2)
  - "With Dr. [T. DeWitt] Talmage" n.d., TMsS, 42 p. (Box 2)
  - "Miss Ellen Terry" n.d., AMs, 2 TMss, 7 p. (Box 2)
  - "Ernest Seaton Thompson" n.d., TMs, 8 p. (Box 2)
  - "Mark Twain" n.d., TMs, 46 p. (Box 2)
  - "Twain and Cable," with autograph comment by Mark Twain n.d., TMs, 5 p. (Box 2)
  - "Twain and Cable." Duplicate version not used. n.d., TMs, 4 p. (Box 2)
  - "Frederick Villiers" n.d., TMs, 2 p. (Box 2)
  - "Lew Wallace," with autograph revisions n.d., 2 TMss, 5 p. (Box 2)
  - "Booker T. Washington," with autograph revisions n.d., 2 TMss, 8 p. (Box 2)
  - "Henry Watterson" n.d., TMs, 4 p. (Box 2)
  - "Walt Whitman" n.d., TMs, 9 p. (Box 2)
  - "William Winter," one with autograph revisions by William Winter n.d., 2 TMss, 24 p. (Box 2)
  - "Sidney Wollett" n.d., TMs, 1 p. (Box 2)
  - "Women Lecturers" n.d., TMs, 36 p. (Box 2)
  - "Israel Zangwill" n.d., TMs, 18 p. (Box 2)
  - "Close" n.d., TMs, 3 p. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous 1900-1903 (Box 2)
  - Photographs and Printed 1900-1903, 64 items (Box 2)
    Photographs and Printed removed from Scrapbooks containing articles and reviews on Eccentricities of Genius: Memories of Famous Men and Women of the Platform and Stage[also contains three photographs of Pond; program for a lecture by Mark Twain, James Whitcomb Riley, and Douglass Sherley at Chickering Hall; an account with publishers G. W. Dillingham Company; program for "The Scotsman War Fund"; and, two obituaries of Pond]
  - Scrapbook 1899-1900, Bound Volume (Box 2)
    Scrapbook containing articles and reviews on Eccentricities of Genius: Memories of Famous Men and Women of the Platform and Stage by James B. Pond
- Bound Voume 1900-1901 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1900-1901 (Box 3)